Professional and personal papers of Edwin Wolf 2nd LCP.EW2
Library Company of Philadelphia
The professional and personal papers of Edwin Wolf 2nd
Bulk, 1920-1988
1798-1996
LCP.EW2
Library Company of Philadelphia
20.0 Linear feet
Edwin Wolf 2nd (1911-1991) was a librarian, bibliophile, author, historian, Franklin scholar, and a civic leader in Philadelphia. Wolf was Curator of the Library Company from 1953 to 1955, and then served as Librarian from 1955 to 1984. During those years, he led the Library Company though a period of rejuvenation, growth, and prosperity. The Edwin Wolf 2nd papers contain correspondence, research files, volumes, publications, photographs, and other records that document the education, career, and personal family life of one of Philadelphia’s most prominent bookmen during the 20th century.
Wolf, Edwin, 2nd.
Provenance
Gift of Edwin Wolf 2nd 1988-1990.
Related Archival Materials note
The Wolf Years: The Renascence of the Library Company of Philadelphia 1952-1984, by Marie Elena Korey. Philadelphia: The Library Company of Philadelphia, 1984.
Photographs of Edwin Wolf are available in the Print and Photograph Department and the LCP Archives.
Painting of Edwin Wolf on display in the Library Company first floor Cataloging Office.
Scope and Contents note
The professional and personal papers of Edwin Wolf 2nd houses the professional and personal records of Edwin Wolf 2nd, Curator (1953-1955) and Librarian (1955-1984) of the Library Company of Philadelphia. This collection, which dates from 1798 to 1996 (with bulk dates of 1920 to 1988), contains correspondence, research files, volumes, publications, photographs, and other records that document the education, career, and personal family life of one of Philadelphia’s most prominent bookmen during the 20th century. The collection is arranged into four series: “I. Personal papers, 1798-1991,” II. Professional records, 1899-1992,” “III. Scholarship, 1833-1996,” and “IV. Photographs by Edwin Wolf 2nd, 1970s.”
Series “I. Personal papers” dates from 1798 to 1991, with bulk dates of 1920 to 1948. This series documents Wolf’s time at the Bedales School in England, his time abroad during his service in World War II, and his family life. Records include photographs, school notebooks, a field notebook from his time in Europe, documenting perceived Nazi activity, and extensive correspondence between Wolf and his parents, between Wolf and his first wife (Peggy) and children, and between Wolf and friends and colleagues. Records also include volumes from Wolf’s personal library (including a family Bible, Wolf’s baby book, and books given as gifts by his colleagues at the Library Company) and honorary degrees awarded to Wolf by University of Pennsylvania and LaSalle University. This series is arranged into three separate runs of records. First in the series is a chronological run of general personal records, followed by a chronological run of volumes from Wolf’s personal library, and ending with a run of family records, arranged by family member.
Series “II. Professional records” dates from 1889 to 1992, with bulk dates of 1930 to 1985, and is broken into two subseries: “IIa. Professional correspondence” and “IIb. Professional affiliations.”
Subseries “IIa. Professional correspondence” dates from 1930 to 1985 and documents Wolf’s professional endeavors while working with Dr. Rosenbach and the Library Company of Philadelphia and contains mostly correspondence. Notable topics include various research projects and interests of both Wolf and his colleagues, appraisal and acquisitions, research services, and professional events and milestones. This subseries is arranged alphabetically by correspondent.
Subseries “IIb. Professional affiliations” dates from 1889 to 1992, with bulk dates of 1931 to 1969. This series documents Wolf’s involvement with many professional and scholarly groups and civic organizations in and around Philadelphia. Records in this subseries include correspondence, reports, notes, pamphlets, meeting minutes, and reports and ephemera related to various professional organization and events. Included in this subseries are materials regarding membership to various scholarly organizations, the notes and reports from Wolf’s survey of the holdings of the Library Company and the Ridgeway Library in 1952, and the citation from Mayor W. Wilson Goode for Wolf’s service on the Mayor’s Cultural Advisory Council and receipt of the Philadelphia Award. This subseries is arranged alphabetically by organization.
Series “III. Scholarship” dates from 1833 to 1996, with bulk dates of 1945 to 1988, and is broken into two subseries: “IIIa. Talks and publications” and “IIIb. Research.” Researchers should note that there is significant overlap between materials and topics in these two subseries.
Subseries “IIIa. Talks and publications” dates from 1895 to 1990, with bulk dates of 1960 to 1988, and contains typescripts, notes, and research materials that document the numerous lectures and addresses given at various meetings, as well as many articles and book reviews. Subjects include the Eighteenth Century Short Title Catalogue, research on the libraries of notable figures in history (William Byrd, Benjamin Chew, Samuel Johnson, James Madison, Benjamin Rush), research on private and public libraries, notices and reviews of publications by Wolf, and correspondence regarding research requests. This subseries is arranged into separate runs of material. First are the talks and publications, followed by a run of additional research materials for talks and publications by Wolf. These first two runs of materials are roughly arranged alphabetically by subject, according to a legacy arrangement. Next is a run of correspondence related to Wolf’s talks and publications (subjects include offprints/reprints and research requests). Last in the subseries is a run of bound reprints of articles and books, mostly published by Wolf, with some published by colleagues. These include newsletters from the Bedales School and William Penn Charter School, yearbooks from summer camp, and articles written by Wolf for several publications, including the JPS Bookmark, Proceedings of the American Philosophical Society, The Pennsylvania Magazine of History and Biography, and Papers of the Bibliographical Society of America. Researchers can find many of the published articles from the beginning of this subseries here.
Subseries “IIIb: Research” dates from 1833 to 1996, with bulk dates of 1945 to 1988. This subseries contains research files, notes, and correspondence relating to Wolf’s diverse research interests, including commonplace books, Benjamin Franklin’s library, and the Polock family. A major component of this subseries is Wolf’s research material and lectures delivered during his tenure as the Lyell Reader in Bibliography at Oxford University. These lectures form the basis for his book The Book Culture of a Colonial American City: Philadelphia Books, Bookmen, and Booksellers. This subseries also contains a run of autographed reprints and offprints from fellow bibliographic scholars and writers, including Whitfied J. Bell, Jr., David Vieth, and Justin G. Turner. This subseries is arranged alphabetically by subject, and chronologically within each subject. The autographed reprints and offprints follow and are arranged alphabetically by publication. Researchers should note that the majority of Wolf’s material on the Polock papers are not physically integrated within this collection; they were processed separately and are not housed with the rest of the Wolf papers.
The final series, “IV. Photographs by Edwin Wolf 2nd,” dates from the 1970s, and contains photographic prints, negatives, contact sheets, and notes from a photography class taken by Wolf. Subjects include landscapes, portraits and candid shots of people, and self-portraits. The materials are arranged by format. Although the subjects of the photographs do not relate directly to Wolf’s tenure at the Library Company, they offer a glimpse into his personal artistic interests towards the end of his life.
The Professional and personal papers of Edwin Wolf, 2nd documents the professional, personal, and civic life of one of the country’s most eminent book scholars, and his diverse research interests in the libraries of many prominent historical figures (including Benjamin Franklin and James Logan), the Polock family, the 1708 Philadelphia charter, the history of the Jews in Philadelphia, book culture in America and colonial Philadelphia, printing and books, and provenance of books. The personal correspondence in this collection provides rich documentation of Wolf’s time in the Army, both while training and while serving in Germany.
Conditions Governing Access note
This collection is open for research use.
Biographical/Historical note
Edwin Wolf 2nd (1911-1991) was a librarian, bibliophile, author, historian, Franklin scholar, and civic leader in Philadelphia. He was born on December 6, 1911 to a German Jewish family in Philadelphia. His father, Morris Wolf, was a founding partner of the law firm Wolf, Block, Schorr and Solis-Cohen. Wolf attended the William Penn Charter School, graduated at age fifteen, and then went on to study at the Bedales School in England. Upon his return to the United States in 1930, he began working for Dr. Abraham Simon Wolf Rosenbach, a famous collector and dealer of rare books, where he learned bibliographical description and cataloging of rare books.
In 1943, Wolf left the employ of Dr. Rosenbach to join the United States Army and serve in World War II. Under the Army Specialized Training Program, he learned German, then was trained in Army intelligence. In 1944, Wolf was sent to Europe, where he was responsible for turning in Nazis with arrest warrants. He also spent part of his service recovering ancient and rare books (including copies of the Gutenberg Bible) that had been hidden throughout the German countryside for protection. Wolf left the Army in 1945 and returned to working for Dr. Rosenbach in 1946.
Upon Dr. Rosenbach’s death in 1952, Wolf joined the Library Company of Philadelphia as a consultant and advisor. He was tasked with surveying the contents of the building (the Ridgeway building at 900 South Broad Street) and make recommendations on the future direction of the Library Company. Wolf found that the institution’s collections were of significant research value, and recommended that the Library Company cease circulation of its holdings and become a scholarly research library specializing in American history and culture to 1880. He also suggested that the collections be cataloged and moved out of the Ridgeway building, which was in deteriorating condition. Wolf was hired to carry out this plan and was named Curator of the Library Company in 1953, and Librarian in 1955.
It was in this capacity that Wolf revitalized the Library Company of Philadelphia. He cataloged the institution’s holdings according to a classification system devised by Wolf to meet the unique needs of the institution and collection and sold duplicate volumes to earn money to increase the Library Company’s holdings and fill in collection gaps. In 1960, he petitioned the Orphan’s Court to sell the Ridgeway building so that the Library Company could build and move into a new building next door to the Historical Society of Pennsylvania.
As Librarian, Wolf made great strides in promoting the Library Company through his Annual Reports (which showcased new acquisitions and the institution’s achievements) and curated exhibitions. He collaborated with the Historical Society of Pennsylvania and the American Philosophical Society to produce catalogs on the subjects of American agriculture, natural history, education, and philanthropy. Wolf’s efforts to revive the Library Company garnered notable donations of books and manuscripts, and also earned funding from grantors and individuals.
Wolf was also a prolific scholar, historian, and writer. His major publications include A History of the Jews of Philadelphia from Colonial Times to the Age of Jackson (co-authored with Maxwell Whiteman), Rosenbach: A Biography (co-authored with John Fleming), and The Library of James Logan of Philadelphia, 1674-1751. He served as associate editor for the volume Philadelphia: A 300-Year History, and wrote and organized the picture book Philadelphia: Portrait of an American City. Wolf was named Lyell Reader in Bibliography at Oxford University for the academic year 1985-1986. The lectures that he gave at Oxford (see the Lyell Lectures in Bibliography in Series IIIb) were developed into a book called The Book Culture of a Colonial American City: Philadelphia Books, Bookmen, and Booksellers. The book Library of Benjamin Franklin was published in 2006 (with Kevin J. Hayes), and was based on Wolf’s extensive research into the library of Benjamin Franklin, which he conducted over his entire career.
Wolf was comprehensively involved in the professional field of rare books and bibliography. He helped found the Philadelphia Area Consortium of Special Collections Libraries, served as President of the Bibliographical Society of America, served on the Board of the Free Library of Philadelphia, was a member of the American Philosophical Society and the American Antiquarian Society, was chairman of the Rare Books and Manuscripts section of the American Library Association, and received honorary degrees from the University of Pennsylvania and LaSalle University.
Wolf was also a civic leader and served with numerous organizations. In the 1940s and 1950s, he worked for the Community Chest, the United Fund, the Young Men’s and Women’s Hebrew Association, and the local Jewish Welfare Board. Wolf acted as President of the Jewish Publication Society of America, the National Foundation of Jewish Culture, and the Federation of Jewish Agencies of Greater Philadelphia. He was an early board member of Philadelphia’s chapter of Americans for Democratic Action. Wolf received the Philadelphia Award in 1982 for his service in the arts in Philadelphia (specifically the Mayor’s Cultural Advisory Board).
Wolf married Margaret (“Peggy”) Gimbel Dannenbaum in 1934, with whom he had three children. Peggy died in a car accident in 1964. In 1965, Wolf was remarried to Mary Paxson Matthews, who had four daughters, three of whom Wolf adopted. Edwin Wolf died at the age of 79 on February 20, 1991, at his home in Philadelphia.
BIBLIOGRAPHY
Korey, Marie Elena. “The Wolf Years: The Renascence of the Library Company of Philadelphia.” Philadelphia: The Library Company of Philadelphia, 1984.
Van Horne, John C. “Edwin Wolf 2nd (6 December 1911-20 February 1991).” Proceedings of the American Philosophical Society, Vol. 137, No. 2, June 1993.
Wolf, Edwin. “An Autobiographical Sketch Written in 1987 and a Bibliography of the Published Writings of Edwin Wolf 2nd.” Philadelphia: The Library Company of Philadelphia, 1991.
Library Company of Philadelphia; Correspondence; Embossed bindings; Libraries; Lyell lectures in bibliography; Philadelphia (Pa.); Photographs; School records
- I. Personal papers, Bulk, 1920-1948; 1798-1991
  - Various loose photographs, circa 1920-1930 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Various loose photographs and photograph albums, circa 1920-1930 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence: From Edwin to various individuals, 1926, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - The William Penn Charter School: Programs, clipping, dance card, notes, draft of debate speech, and application to Haverford College, 1927, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - The William Penn Charter School: American History notebook, circa 1927 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Bedales School: Cricket, tennis, football, and lacrosse fixture cards, 1927-1929 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Bedales School: Playbills, 1927-1930 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Bedales School: Term reports, 1927-1930 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Bedales School: Photograph of Leslie Scott and envelope, circa 1927-1930 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Bedales School: Various writings and assignments, circa 1927-1930 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Bedales School: Notices, pamphlets, invitations, 1927-1930, 1932, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Bedales School: The Royal Life Saving Society instruction booklet, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Bedales School: Spring term fees receipt, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Bedales School: "Aliens Order, 1920. Certificate of Registration", 1928-1930 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Travel: Hotel bills, itinerary, White Star Line passenger lists, 1928-1931, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Bedales School: Exams, circa 1927-1930 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Bedales School: Latin notebooks, circa 1927-1930 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Bedales School: History notebooks, circa 1927-1930 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Bedales School: Greek notebooks, circa 1927-1930 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Bedales School: English essay notebooks, circa 1927-1930 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Bedales School: Class photographs (oversize), 1928-1930 (Map-case 1)
  - Bedales School: Correspondence, 1929-1931 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence: Between Peggy and her parents, circa 1920s (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence: From Edwin to his parents, circa 1920s (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Travel: Menus, brochures, postcards, regarding Italy, Santo Domingo, and others, circa 1920s-1930s (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Bedales School: Class schedules for spring and summer terms, 1930 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Cigar box labels, circa 1930 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence: From Edwin to his family, 1930-1934, undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Library philanthropy: Receipts of gifts by Edwin to Franklin Institute, Free Library of Philadelphia, Library Company of Philadelphia, Philadelphia school districts, and J. C. Brown Library, letter from W. Earl Smith to H. Blum, facsimile of a letter written by John Adams, pamphlet list of materials desired by the Princeton Library, Research News of the Clements Library, letter from N. Taylor to Edwin, and book dealer contract (typescript) of Rosenbach representative Arthur D. MacCoy, 1933-1965, undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Collecting activities, Lord Nelson: Letters between Edwin and MacMillan and Company, P. Fitzhugh Stryker, James Normile, D. H. Coblentz, M. Butlin, Arthur Swann, John Carter, and J. Fairbanks (9 items), essay entitled “Four Letters From William Hayley to Emma Hamilton,” photographs of paintings related to Lord Nelson, Bruce Gimelson Autographs dealer catalogue, The First Hundred, clippings regarding Nelson/Hamilton love letters held at Free Library of Philadelphia, 1934, 1937, 1962-1968, undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Bedales School: Letter from B. H. Crumb to Edwin, appealing for endowment funds, and copies of Bedales Chronicle, 1935 June 9, 1958, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Financial records: Cancelled checks, 1937, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Financial records: Tuition receipts, household expenses, household inventory, 1937, 1942, 1984, undated (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence: To Edwin from J. Sloane, I. Schamberg, R. A. Hunter, J. F. Lewis, Frederick Goff, A. L. Sacher, and L. J. Rosenwald (25 letters, 1 postcard [3 without dates]), 1937 May 19-1967 January 1, undated (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Financial records: Various receipts, bills, notes, and stock and bond registers, 1930s (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence: To Edwin from various individuals, 1930s (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence: To Edwin from his parents, 1930s, undated (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence: From Edwin to his parents, circa 1930 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence: To Edwin and Peggy, circa 1930s-1940s (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence: To Edwin from various individuals, circa 1930s-1940s (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence: To Edwin from Babette, circa 1930s-1940s (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence: Wedding invitations, 1938-1942 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence: Christmas cards, 1938-1942, undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence: Between Edwin and Seymour Dribben (11 letters), 1939 November 27-1942 November 2 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence: Between Edwin and others, including Earle Haggerty, W. H. Sylk, Phillip Kind, Jr., Oscar Kind, Louis Levinthal, and Y. A. Schekter. Also includes grade card of Margaret Dannenbaum Wolf at Temple University and wills of Edwin M. Dannebaum and Gertrude Gimbel Dannebaum, 1940 January 5-1968 September 15 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence and other materials related to military service, 1940-1945 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Clipping regarding Rosenbach 16th century suit of armor donated to scrap metal drive, circa 1942 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence: From Edwin to his parents, 1943 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence: To Edwin from various individuals, 1943 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Change of address forms, 1943, 1945 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence: From Edwin to Peggy, 1943, undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence: From Edwin to Peggy, 1944 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence: To Edwin from various individuals, 1944 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence: From Edwin to Peggy, 1945 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence: From Edwin to his parents, 1945 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence: From Edwin to various individuals, 1945 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Military notebook, circa 1945 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Collecting activities, Lord Nelson: Letters between Edwin and H. S. Mott, D. Pollen, L. Rosenwald, S. Davis, A. H. Able, S. Moyerman, and Paul C. Richards (12 items), 1948 December 31-1963 May 21 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Library philanthropy: Letters to Edwin from Mrs. Marny Max-Muller, R. F. Metzdorf, W. L.Fox, and L. Massey, funding application for the Stephen Memorial Library, American Philosophical Society Committee on the 1974 library annual report, 1949 May 24-1964 February 12, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence: To Edwin from Peggy, circa 1940s (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Assorted clippings, circa 1940s (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence: To Peggy from various individuals, circa 1940s-1950s (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Assorted records: Book plates, poem, written sheet music, business cards, program from Gimbel Philadelphia Award luncheon, circa 1940s-1960s (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence: Between Edwin and others, including Lessing J. Rosenwald and W. Annenberg (7 letters), 1949 October 27-1950 December 14 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence: To Edwin from various individuals, 1950 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Americans for Democratic Action: Meeting flyer, letters, and memoranda, 1950-1951 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence: From Edwin to his parents, 1952 July 4 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Blank stationery and stamps, 1955, undated (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence: Letter from Edwin to Mary, 1961 July 15 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Certificate from Massachusetts Historical Society and honorary degrees awarded by LaSalle University and University of Pennsylvania, 1965, 1981, 1982, 1992 (Box 37, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence: To Edwin from various individuals, circa 1960s-1980s (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence: To Edwin from various individuals (18 letters), 1975-1982 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Photograph of Edwin receiving honorary degree from LaSalle University and transcipt of the acceptance ceremony, circa 1981 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence: To Edwin from various individuals regarding The Philadelphia Award (58 items), 1982 February-May (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Watercolor painting by Joseph Powell, 1982 September 26 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Pamphlet for speaker series at Congregation Rodeph Shalom entitled "Jewish Moral Dilemmas for the 1990's" (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Catalogue: "Books Printed at the Elzevier Press from the Library of the Late Edwin Wolf II", circa 1990 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Talk given by Jim Green at memorial service for Edwin Wolf II, 1991 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence: To Edwin from Marie Lou, undated (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Reproduction prints of engravings, undated (Map-case 1)